hi everyone welcome to lecture 11 of 188
let's start with a couple of
announcements project two was due last
week Friday but there's a mini contest
that's optional in which you get to
compete with other agents staff agents
and in the future other student agents
on the board where on one side you are
ghosts you supposed to defend your
territory and the other side you're
pac-man is supposed to go eat the food
pallets and bring them back but if the
ghosts catch you on the other side
before you bring them back then you
explode back into food pallets and you
get reset so this optional contest ends
on Sunday currently on leaderboard at
number one we have yzs it's yzs here
right there congratulations at number
two we have team no bug are they here
keep no bug over there congratulations
and number three we have you chan woo
over here congratulations so we have
till Sunday for this contest and we'll
round up results of the final
leaderboard likely next week you can get
extra credit by being near the top of
the leaderboard or also by beating staff
agents so independent of what the other
students do if you beat enough staff
agents the results extra credit for that
0.5 points for every staff agent you
beat sufficiently often so that's with a
Sunday timeline homework 5 was released
and is due on Monday as usual it has
three components
there is the electronic part there's the
written part and then there is a
self-assessment of the previous written
as part of the homework project three
reinforcement learning is also released
and it's due next week Friday at 4 p.m.
any questions about logistics
okay let's dive into the technical
accountants then this our second lecture
on reinforcement learning this is her
minor what's going on in reinforcement
learning we will still assume there's a
market decision process what does that
mean that there's a set of states a set
of actions which might depend what's
available on which state you're in there
is a underlying model that says what is
the probability of landing in state s
prime if you were in state s and took
action a and there's a reward function
that tells you if you're in state s took
action a landed in s prime how much
reward did you get or will you get when
it happens again and what we're looking
for is a policy PI of s that tells us
for every state what is the best thing
to do where best is defined as
maximizing expected discounted sum of
future rewards the twist in
reinforcement learning is that we don't
know
dear R so we have to experiment in the
world to figure out how it works how the
transitions are and where the reward is
to then from that maybe figure out how
we can then optimize how much reward we
collect the big idea we covered last
time is that you can compute averages
instead of having access to T and we'll
review some of that now big picture wise
with Markov decision processes and
reinforced running a total of four
lectures what have we seen in the first
two lectures the MVP was known there
were two types of techniques we looked
at we looked at computing optimal value
V star automotive value Q star optimal
policy PI star we have two algorithms
for that policy tuition and value
iteration they assume access to the
model and to the reward function and
then we also saw you can evaluate a
policy
so somebody fixes a policy you can
evaluate it see what the value is and
that's called policy evaluation which
you can do in two ways
it turns out you can do it just like
Valerie iteration but instead of having
a max over actions the action is fixed
to whatever the policy prescribes and so
it's like being in a new MVP we're only
one actions available in every state and
it's running validation that new MVP
just it's a very simple MVP or the
action is fixed for every state that's
policy valuation one way to do it the
other thing that happened is once we got
rid of that max in the valuation
equation it becomes a linear equation so
could also just solve a linear system of
equations to find the values of a policy
that's when we know the model and we
know the reward function then last
lecture we started looking at what if we
don't know the model and/or the reward
function and we saw there's two ways of
tackling this the model-based approach
is one where we say okay let's collect
data from that data estimate TNR and
then we can reuse the techniques you
already know and that's model-based
reinforcement learning so that's one way
to do it another way to do is to say
well actually rather than learning the
models we can directly learn values q
functions policies we saw this in two
ways we saw first value learning under
value learning we saw two approaches we
saw direct evaluation where we just look
from a state every time we were there
how much reward they would get in the
future and averaged it and we saw
temporal difference learning or indirect
evaluation where we used the bellman
equation by the sampled version two from
every experience update our estimate of
the value of the state we were just in
and we saw then that we can also do this
with Q values and that has a lot of
benefits because if you do with Q values
it also tells us what action to take in
any given state so that's what we'll
look at more today and expand on what we
cover there so in model free learning
what we have is effectively a stream of
experience and from that stream of
experience you want to somehow learn
something and we want to do it whenever
there is a transition an entity of this
type so one part of that stream we want
to update what we know so far
and the way we've done is by mimicking
the bellman equation but doing in a
sample based way rather than requiring
access to the model let's take a look
again at how that worked this is the
bellman equation for Q values what does
it say it says the value for being in
state s and taking action a if we have K
plus 1 steps yet to live in the life of
the agent is equal to a sum over states
that we might land in and it's a
weighted sum based on the probability of
landing in that state the reward we get
for that transition plus a discount
factor gamma times what we expect to get
in the future and in the future there's
only K steps left now so that this is QK
we start from q0 equals 0 and can work
our way up to any k going up one at a
time why a max here well we're trying to
compute the optimal Q values and so when
we think about what is the value from
the current state in action it's the
reward we got instantaneously Plus what
we expect to get if we act optimally
from that onwards and optimally from
then onwards means that we need to take
the optimal action over all traces of
action available at that next state s
prime of course now we wanted to compute
this without knowing TN r and TN are a
featured quite prominently in here so
what we do is we experience a transition
as a our s prime what that gives us is
in some sense the ability to compute one
such term in this way that sum so this
is our sample estimate based on just one
of these terms of course we don't want
to just say that the q value for state s
action is equal to this because there
could be many future states s Prime and
this is just one that we experienced out
of many possible future States s prime
so we're going to do an averaging over
the many times we were in state s and
took action a what was the sample
estimate of the value so the way we
average is with a running average who
don't have to keep everything around
with sirki our current running
is qsa we have a new sample estimate
this one over here we're going to
average them together in a weighted way
if alpha is 1/2 then we have 1/2 what we
used to have 1/2 the new sample estimate
and practice alpha will be much smaller
than 1/2 so the sample update the update
here will be dominated by this term over
here but a little bit of an adjustment
based on this term here any questions
about this this will be the foundation
for the first half of lecture today yes
yeah it's a good question so you could
say well and sometimes the question is
how do we even choose alpha if alpha is
fixed then what we get is the latest
ones contribute more than the early ones
because they get down weighted over time
so you can think of it as a feature or
as a bun let's think about this well if
the later ones get more weight in the
result than the earlier ones the reason
we might like that is because as we've
been doing this for a while the Q values
become more and more accurate and as the
Q values become more accurate than the
sample estimate that we compute here
will be a more accurate one than the one
we had before and so the later
experiences result in sample estimates
that are more accurate than the early
experiences and so that's why we
actually consider it a good thing that
the later ones
contribute more than the earlier ones
but in principle if you wanted them all
to contribute equally you you could
probably find a calculation to do that
in practice we don't care about that we
rather have the later ones contribute
more and it happens to also be very
convenient because then we can do this
exponential weighted average for which
we don't need to keep as much
information around any other questions
okay let's build on this done what are
some of the properties the update
equation we just looked at if we use it
often enough meaning we collect enough
experience the Q values will converge to
the optimal Q values even if you're
acting sub-optimally and this is very
surprising because typically when you
try to compute values like we saw in the
standard value evaluation type setup you
would compute the value of the current
policy but with this update equation and
this is because of the max that's
happening in here here that max
makes it that the samples are
referencing the optimal policy even if
the way you collect your data is not
optimally in fact it never be optimal
initially because you don't know how to
do things optimally and so this is off
policy learning that max in there
enables of policy learning allows us to
use any policy to collect data not any
there are a few caveats that we'll look
at but any policy that visits every
state action pair sufficiently often is
okay and will result in the optimal Q
values what are these caveats candidates
are you have to explore enough more
about that later but one way to think of
this you need to somehow satisfy the
condition that every state action pair
is visited infinitely often your alpha
has to go down otherwise you don't get
convergence because the updates remain
too big over time so gradually decaying
your alpha but don't decay too quickly
is if they decay too quickly
you've only averaged a small amount of
experience together and it won't have
conversion yet to the right average in
the limit doesn't matter how you select
actions as long as these things are
satisfied so let's look at a demo to
remind us of how this works we have so
here we're gonna watch a Q learning
agent which the presence of which you
can see with the blue dot and it's gonna
run on its own so I'm not moving it
around to let it run faster it's gonna
run on its own and it's running in this
grid world which
happens to have a bunch of terminal
states at the bottom also terminal state
all the way up the right that's actually
a good one
the bottom line is actually pretty bad
to be at believe it's negative 100
reward when you end up exiting from
there and the policy we see run here is
a non optimal policy often jumps off the
cliff and the thing that paid things to
pay attention to here is that if you
look in the optimal path indeed it's
converging onto a value of roughly 10
which is the optimal value of the
discount factor is one you can also see
that even when it jumps off the cliff it
retains the optimal values because it
knows that that was not the optimal
action the update happens based on the
max of Q values not based on the action
you actually took and so jumping off the
cliff does not affect the values I get
propagated back except of course for the
action from where you actually do the
jumping off the cliff from which it's
irreversible where it has to affect it
all the downward actions from the middle
row there are some places it's barely
ever been that's something we'll address
I mean in principle there might be
something really good there that it
hasn't found out about yet because it
hasn't explored very fully but overall
after a while it converges to roughly
the right values in the places at least
in the middle and the bottom and this is
happening despite acting fairly randomly
so the notion of needing to visit every
state action pair sufficiently often is
actually a tricky one because it
requires that you somehow understand
where you've been where you've not been
or and somehow make sure that you are
there in all places often enough simple
example would be in real world let's say
you have your usual place to go for
lunch and it's pretty good see pretty
happy every time you go there but then a
new place has its grand opening and now
you have to make a decision are you
gonna try it out it's risky it's
probably worse because you're so happy
with your usual lunch place but if you
don't try it you'll never know and so if
you want to make sure you have the
optimal policy you have to go try this
new place if it's bad you might never go
back but then maybe it's a good place
and it's more optimal and you keep going
there but without trying you won't know
and that's a critical aspect of
exploration you'll have to try things
and many of them that you'll try will
actually not be good for you
but you didn't know ahead of time you
have to try to find out so what's a very
simple scheme for exploration something
called Epsilon greedy it's very simple
and actually used surprisingly often
every time step your agent will flip a
coin and with some small probability
Epsilon so the coin is biased and with a
small probability epsilon comes up one
way probability 1 minus epsilon comes up
the other way Preble the epsilon it'll
act randomly probably 1 minus Epsilon
it'll look at the current Q values look
at which action is optimal based on the
current estimates of the Q values take
that action so this introduces
randomness while usually playing
according to the strategy that you think
is best and so what does this do well it
ensures that while you're learning you
usually do pretty good things which you
might want so you're not just always
acting randomly but it also ensures that
you have random is in there and if you
run this long enough every state action
pair will be visited sufficiently often
and you will have your Q values converge
to the optimal Q values let's take a
look
this inaction on the crawler so what are
you going to watch here we're gonna have
the crawler robot again you're gonna
work with that robot in your project
three now this interface here will start
making more sense what do we have here
we have an EPS explicit epsilon it's
right now a 0.8
that's how pretty high that means
that with probability 0.8 actions are
taken randomly probability zero point to
the current Q function estimate is
followed
who said this count factor there is a
learning rate and then there is some
things we can use to accelerate the
learning meaning we can not watch
everything live but let it behind the
scenes collect a lot more experience so
let's take a look at this up and running
with epsilon equals 0.8 so this thing is
acting mostly randomly at this point so
it's not really going anywhere
but we also know that's kind of okay we
know to learn good Q values we don't
need to act according to any optimal
policy as long as we get good coverage
and so if we see this thing get good
coverage we can expect it to learn a
good policy
now we skip forward 30,000 steps so it's
quite a little more experience skip
forward a million steps now through
these random actions it's seen pretty
much everything but if we look at it
it's still not acting that great why is
that it's actually learned the optimal Q
values but it's still using an Epsilon
that's 0.8 and so most of the time it's
not using those Q values to decide what
to do and so it's still behaving fairly
poorly but it's actually learned things
underneath I mean we can't know that
from just what we've seen so far but we
can hope for that and soon we will decay
epsilon smaller and see that indeed when
it starts listening to its Q values it's
gonna do really really well but as long
as epsilon is large it's never gonna
work all that well but it's learning
doing a little better than initially
with this large epsilon but do you
really see what it's learned we got to
start decaying Epsilon so let's
decay Epsilon bring it down to maybe
zero point zero or even zero completely
pure exploitation no random is anymore
and it's steadily making progress so now
we can see what it learned now something
you can in channel do with your Q
learning agent periodically switch to a
Q that is an epsilon that is zero
to see what it's learned so far okay
so this worked eventually after we skip
forward many many many episodes we had
to lower epsilon over time to make sure
we see better behavior so that's
something we need to keep in mind if we
actually want to get good behavior out
but we didn't have anything automatic
and what we're gonna look at now is
something called exploration functions
that will help us decay the exploration
automatically based on how much you have
already learned once you've learned a
lot you should maybe explore less okay
so we want to explore random actions are
good in some sense but they explore a
fixed amount a better idea is to pay
attention to the parts of the space
where you don't know much yet if you
don't know much yet you should try
things out you haven't seen yet but if
you already know how things work there
is no reason to again do random things
okay so initially you don't know you
need to go check it out but then once
you've been there you don't want to keep
randomly checking it out what we're
going to use this something called an
exploration function let me say
something about that f here it's a
function that combines two things an
estimate of what will be a utility you
and then takes in also account so for
each state action combination will keep
track of a utility and account and
rather than just choosing an action
based on its expected utility will
choose an action based on expected
utility plus this correction this
correction K is a constant let's say
maybe it's 10 who knows some number and
it's how often we've seen that state
action pair maybe we'll want to n plus 1
here just to make sure
when we're at zero it doesn't divide up
to infinity but so what happens here is
when you've been somewhere only zero
times this will be K once you've been
somewhere two times it'll be K over 2
once you've been somewhere a hundred
times will be K over 100 and so the more
often you've been somewhere the lower
the second quantity becomes and so the
less you add to how you perceive the
utility of exercising that state action
pair so what would it mean regular queue
updates look like this and this is a
shorthand notation for a weighted update
we already have an estimate of Q we're
gonna have a new sample estimate of Q
and we're going to combine it 1 minus
alpha the old thing plus alpha the new
thing that's what this means we're gonna
replace this now instead of using this
over here we're going to correct it so
we're going to look for all actions that
are available in state s Prime
we're going to look at the Q values
associated with action a prime in Status
prime but also look at how often have we
been in status Prime and taken action a
prime and this thing here will be
computed which will give a bonus to
actions that haven't been taken very
often yet in that state so now we're
going to be favoring actions we haven't
taken very often yet what does actually
mean to favor these actions what it
means is that when we compute the sample
estimate in this calculation over here
we'll end up with higher values so what
that really means is that if we're
looking at the value of state s and
action a and we wonder how much is this
really worth it take action a state s
they'll say well that depends on whether
in state s prime there are there are
high Q values but also in state s prime
are there actions available we haven't
taken very often yet
and if there are actions available in s
prime that you haven't taken very often
yet and you can reach s prime from
taking action in state s then that will
start forever
that action a instead us so you're kind
of thinking ahead here with this update
you're saying how good is my action not
just in terms of reward I'm gonna get
but in terms of landing in a state s
prime where there are actions available
I have not explored much yet and so and
this will of course propagate back to
the next one next one next one and we
will build up over time is Q values
they're not the actual Q values
initially but that estimate whether a
certain action gives you exploration
potential and if an action is high
exploration potential you're more likely
to take it and so if that means if you
have a complicated environment or maybe
need to run down a very long hallway and
behind a hoe it is a huge room with a
lot of things to explore then this thing
will encourage you to go down that
hallway until you've explored everything
in that room and once you have explored
everything in that room sufficiently
often then these bonuses will start to
decay because the counts will be high
and the bonus is based on one over the
count these bonuses will start to decay
you'll stop visiting that room or maybe
if there's actually a real value in that
room thanks to high Q values there
you'll still keep going there and go
collect rewards so it's a much more
structured way of doing exploration than
just in the moment picking something
random any questions about this yes
so let's say we have a hallway a bunch
of states and then here we have a
massive room and maybe here we have a
hallway going another way but only a
small room if your run standard epsilon
greedy based exploration we will let's
say we start out here we'll end up
spending less than half of our time in
this room and more than half our time on
this side that's not good we don't get a
whole lot now your question is why do we
do better with this approach is it
really true that we're doing better with
this approach let's think about this so
let's say we go down this hallway first
time we go down what will happen is
based on novelty there will be updates
on the to the state's before because we
had actions available in the next state
that make that state look good these
updates based on hi-hi exploration bonus
because n is still low will initially
favor all states here then your question
is after you've been down the hallway
many many times what will happen well
what happened is they will still be high
because you'll still experience new
things somewhere in this room and they
will back propagate through these
updates into the states in the hallway
until at some point there is no bonus
anymore to be collected from this big
room at which point these Q values will
start dropping down because we will no
contributions anymore from the
exploration bonus so even so the main
point here is that even if exploration
bonuses might not be that high anymore
intrinsically in the moment if you just
think of them as rewards because they
propagate in the Q values you'll still
continue to favor going down that
hallway any other questions about this
okay let's take let's take a look at
crawler with a exploration function so
this same setup as before epsilon is
still 0.1 to ensure that there's at
least initially a little bit of
randomness because if epsilon is zero
initially then you already have a
deterministic policy and you're now
going to see multiple things to see that
there are exploration bonuses so your
epsilon is non zero but pretty small so
your behavior will be dominated by the Q
function with an exploration function
what that means will be dominated by a
combination of how novel are the things
available to me after I take this action
and how much reward is available to me
and after I take this action let's run
this this time we're not gonna jump
forward by skipping 30,000 steps or a
million steps we're just letting it run
live and so we're actually in just about
10 20 seconds see this thing learn to do
things right now there's still a lot of
exploration still a lot of things that
hasn't tried and so it's doing a lot of
things to learn more but then at some
point the exploration bonus starts to
decay because you've seen things before
you've tried them before then that
propagates in the Q values which then
become dominated by actual reward and it
starts exploiting and so here we got
something in just order of a few hundred
or thousand steps rather than needing to
skip forward a million steps before we
get good behavior okay so that's Q
learning with exploration there's some
other concept that's good to be aware of
it's called regret it's a term that you
know in real life it's when you do
something and you wish you hadn't done
it maybe some people are thinking about
that right now in Washington not sure so
there is a notion in AI also about
regret and it's actually quite related
to the real-life notion at least the one
of wishing you hadn't done something you
did
more formally when we have an algorithm
we could try to compare them just based
on do they get to an optimal policy or
we could compare them based on how
quickly do they achieve an optimal
policy for example we know Epsilon
greedy queue learning and exploration
function key learning both ultimately
achieve optimal policies so how can we
quantify that notion that we believe one
of them is slightly better than another
one well one way to do this is to say
let's see during the learning how much
reward was accumulated let's have this
thing run let's say for ten million
steps and see over the entire duration
how much reward was accumulated not just
how good is at the end but in the entire
process then all of a sudden you're
measuring how fast the learning is not
just how good the learning is when it's
done so regret measures the difference
in that sense if you had an optimal
learner that learned as quickly as
possible versus your learner what's the
difference and so random exploration
will have much higher regret than a
exploration function based learner no
you're never gonna have zero regret by
the way in reinforced Malinin because if
you don't know how the world works you
still have to try things out and find
out whether they're good or bad but
different approaches will have less
regret if they're better okay so so far
we've looked at exact methods that is
methods that give us the exact solution
we need if we run it long enough now
we're going to look at ways of
approximating the solution it's the
first type of approximation we'll do and
we'll see a lot more approximation in
the later half of the course but we'll
see already one pretty basic machine
learning idea today so what we're
interested in is generalizing across
states when we look at basic cue
learning it's nice it keeps track of a
table of all Q values and that's good if
you can fit all your Q values in a small
table but in realistic situations the
number of states to visit is very very
large and you will now be able to
store a table with a Q value for every
state action pair so if you can't do
that how are you gonna run Q learning
well maybe you say I just buy a bigger
computer to store everything but let's
say that even that will not do the job
for you the space is too large you
cannot store a Q Valley for the state
action pair okay
well the key idea is going to be that we
want to generalize we want to learn
about a small number of training states
from experience and then generalize that
experience to do well a new situation
we've not been in before but it all
related
simple example would be maybe you've
never been in some new building before
if you've been in other buildings and
from having been in other buildings you
know that you know trying a door is a
good idea to try to get into a building
even though you never tried that door
before you never been in that specific
state before you knew it from other
experience can we get the same thing
here so you don't need to relearn
everything in a new state especially not
if it's related to things you've seen in
the past let's take a look at pac-man in
action so first we will look at pac-man
running Q learning in a very small world
and we'll just see
pac-man learning from scratch a lot of
losses because initially the key valleys
aren't all that good in fact mostly
losses but sometimes the win
get some as some better reward and might
learn from that how to do better in the
future but it doesn't learn too quickly
okay this is taking a long time
I'll send Q learning you don't want to
watch everything in detail let me try to
close this let's now have it silently
train for 2000 episodes and then after
that we'll watch it again
so it's trained silently or it is
training signle for 2000 episodes it's
becoming better and nominally has Q
function that describes a pretty good
policy and it seems to usually win so
this took about two thousand episodes
such a very small world there's only six
positions for pac-man six positions for
the ghosts there's one food palate but
2,000 episodes to learn very long time
let's look at a slightly bigger one
let's look at still very small but it's
just slightly bigger well North action
was interesting to try it first
here's trying some other things you look
at it it seems like it's pretty dumb why
is it not doing the right thing well
actually it's in new States the
experiencing things has never
experienced before to us they look
similar because being eaten by the ghost
doesn't matter which query you're on
you're eaten but for pac-man being
eating that squared to 2 might be very
different from being eaten that's square
to 3 because there's a different state
and so needs to learn a different value
for that if you're um standard
q-learning
and so we want to get away from that we
don't want to have to relearn that but
getting eaten by a ghost what that means
in every single square same thing for
eating a food palate and so forth we
want to somehow generalize experience
and that should lead to much faster
learning ok so to make this even more
explicit imagine you run q-learning and
you have discovered that this state is a
bad state well seems a good thing to
have learned now what if you're in this
state that's almost the same state but
actually it's just a different entry in
the cute table and it doesn't if you do
stammer q-learning you know nothing
about this how about this one I mean
this is extremely similar to that first
one spot the differences up here small
difference one food palate is not there
but in the cue table is just a different
entry and you have learned nothing about
that new entry from your past experience
if you use regular tabular q-learning
ok we've seen those in action so what
can we do you've actually seen this
before in lecture
five I believe let's see maybe see games
lecture seven lecture seven in games we
looked at evaluation functions
evaluations functions was this thing
where you said to decide how good a
situation is I can't run all the way
till the end of the game to evaluate it
because the minimax calculation is just
too much what I'm going to do is just
have an estimate and that estimate is
some weighted sum of different
contributing factors so for example
distance to closest ghost that might be
important in evaluating how good your
current situation is distance to closest
thought number of ghosts may be one over
the distance two dots squared is pac-man
in a tunnel or not you're in a tunnel
you might get corn and more easily so
maybe that's not as good a place to be
and many more and so what you do there
is you design a set of features and
these features evaluate some aspects of
the current situation that you think
contribute to how good that situation is
and then ashame your project to you
played with those features and how to
sum them together in a weighted fashion
that this might come out well we're
gonna get new now and Q learning is that
we'll learn how to combine these
features in the right way so more
concretely we could how to do is for
value learning or for Q learning let's
focus on the Q learning one will now say
our Q function is a weighted sum of
feature values and the weights here
rather than setting them by hand and us
saying oh I think this is the ghost is
so much more important than this is the
food palate maybe ten here one there
rather than doing that we're gonna run Q
learning and we're gonna expect from Q
learning to learn these weights such
that once you've learned them these Q
values computed using those weights are
hopefully fairly precise Q values will
they be perfect probably not because
it's unlikely that we hear weighted sum
of features that you can represent the
exact optimal Q function but hopefully
you can get pretty close with your way
that sum
features and learn something that's very
useful as a consequence to act in a new
environment and also you can learn a lot
more quickly because thanks to these
features if you're in new states where
similar features trigger you already
know something about those states before
you've ever been there this advantage to
keep in mind is that if you don't have
enough features it could be that two
states as far as the features are
concerned are identical and that means
you cannot distinguish them anymore with
your Q function so you look at your
features and if you find two states that
you think are really really different
and one is really good the other one is
really bad but they have the exact same
feature values there's no way you're
killing agent your approximate cue any
agent can just doing the summation
anymore because the only thing I can do
is interpret the state through the
feature values okay let's see actually
let's take our small break here and then
look at how this works after the break
all right any questions about the first
half of lecture
yes
so the question is why do we use this
specific form factor to approximate our
Q values there are many choices that can
be made there one nice thing about
having a linear combination of features
is that the learning updates we'll see
are simpler to understand there are ways
to make this nonlinear and we will look
at that at the very end of the course
but for now we're gonna assume that we
have a set of features and that the Q
function that we want to fit is a
weighted combination of those features
but we'll revisit that assumption
maybe I'm lecture 20 or something or 22
okay so we want to do approximate Q
learning now so we want to learn these
weights from experiences okay let's take
a look at how this works we have a
transition and based on this transition
we want to get a better estimate of
these weights well just like before we
can look at the difference between the
sample estimate of the Q function for
state s and action a with our current
approximation so far so this is the
current sample and this is the
approximation so far then in traditional
Chi learning what we do is we'd say okay
we have our estimate and we're going to
correct it by some scale factor alpha
times the difference and nudge it in the
direction of the sample we just saw
effectively but not necessarily all the
way there that's why alpha is gonna be
smaller than one because it's just a
sample and we need to average many
samples to know what it really should be
so we just nudge it in that direction
but now we don't have a table in which
to store such updates we can definitely
retrieve q si for the state action that
we just experienced we just need to run
this evaluation here weighted sum of the
features for that state action pair but
we don't have a table to store this
update into and we also don't want to
have such tab
we want to instead update the weights
rather than table with Q values turns
out that this is the update you end up
with in case you want to update the
weights it's not derived on this slide
will see some intuition behind the
derivation of some later slides but for
now let's interpret this update what
does this say it's saying that the
weight for feature I is whatever the
weight for future I was plus some
learning rate times the difference times
the feature value let's think about this
let's say the difference is positive
okay and for now let's assume that the
feature values are either 0 or 1 okay
then if the feature value is 0 nothing
changes to the weights so this was a
state action pair where the feature
value was 0 was not active and nothing
changes about the weight because it's a
state where that feature isn't present
now what did the future value is 1 what
happens well the future value is 1 and
the difference is positive meaning that
the sample was higher than our estimate
that we have then we get a positive
update on the weight what's the result
of that we make the weight more positive
that more positive weight would get
multiplied with this feature value which
is 1 in our current assumption which
would increase the Q value at state si
so we see we have the right behavior in
terms of direction that it goes when
feature values one difference is
positive weight goes up which results in
our Q estimate also going up which is
what we want gets nudged in the right
direction now what if the difference is
negative meaning that the experience we
got through the sample was lower than we
had anticipated based on our current Q
function approximation well then the way
it will be nudged down and that's also
what we want because the weight gets
nudged down then that means if we
reevaluate the Q value for si it's now
going to be lower than it was before
because and lower weight was multiplied
with one resolving a lower some of these
weighted
features okay so for the zero one case
we get a behavior that makes a lot of
sense now to generalize this
interpretation imagine have a feature
that is more continuous in range maybe
it can go from negative 10 to +10 then
what's going to happen let's first think
about it being +10 so as high as it can
possibly get and let's say our
experience is such that the difference
is positive we got more than we expected
from our sample well if our feature
value is 10 very high and we got a
positive difference here then the weight
will go up if another feature was only
one the difference is still the same
it's positive then it'll go up that
weight by only 1 so we see here is that
if your feature was more active the
weight will go up by more so whenever
something's very active there'll be a
big correction how big depends of course
on the difference and in which direction
depends on the difference if the
difference is positively a correction
the positive version difference is
negative in the negative direction but
we see that the correction is scaled by
how big our feature was and that makes
sense like the feature takes on a high
value it's a feature that's dominating
how we think about that particular state
and so if there's a correction to be
made for that state the weights
associated with those features should be
updated the most whereas if a feature is
very close to zero then a feature
doesn't play much of a role in that
state and so when we do an update even
when the difference might be relatively
high it gets multiplied with this low
number any one update very much for
those weights okay so now I know how to
interpret this and if things are
negative then things will work out too
and there'll be no double negatives that
cancel out the right way so what's
happening underneath is weights get
adjusted and more adjustment when
there's a bigger difference and when
your features take on bigger values in
absolute sense okay
let's we'll see a formal verification in
a couple slides but let's first take a
look at this in action imagine you are
in a pac-man world and you have two
features
one related to distance to the closest
dot and another one related to distance
to the ghost closest ghost maybe and so
maybe you initialized as you say well I
think being close to a ghost is not good
so maybe I should have something where
somehow it countries in the opposite way
where distance is actually good so this
is actually not a good initialization we
wouldn't like this negative one you
really would want goes to be far away so
a large distance should be positive but
this is just how you initialized it okay
let's see what what happens we have a
world we have a current experience we
take the action north we'll get from
that the next state and a reward it was
a pretty bad action we got eaten by the
ghost reward is minus 500 and the Q
value of s Prime there's only no actions
available the games over is zero no
reward anymore when the game is over
okay so that gives us a sample estimate
our sample estimate is minus 500 what
was our actual estimate well that's
based on this equation over here it's 4
times F dot which is 0.5 so that
contributes to here and then negative 1
times 1 which is a negative 1
some that together gives us plus 1 so
our estimate used to be plus 1 for the
state action pair our sample says
negative 500 so we need to revise this
down what will the update do it will say
ok
for each weight we update it by a low
nudge in the direction the difference
says in which direction and then
multiply it with the feature vector and
so here the first one the feature
value is 0.5 second one one after the
update we get this approximation for our
Q value of course just one update it's
not enough we'll need to keep doing this
to get better Q values over time but
that's mechanically what happens
underneath now let's justify this so
actually let's watch it in action first
before we justify it
we'll run the approximate q-learning and
a pretty big grid no six hasn't the
first one didn't realize the ghosts are
bad but now it's done an update and
hopefully it realizes being close to
ghost is bad but it still didn't
anticipate it well enough definitely
knows food palettes are good it's a lot
of reward in those and now it seems to
have learned that staying away from
ghosts is a good thing
it hasn't explored the power palettes so
it doesn't know anything about those
it's possible that the random
initialization of the weights in front
of the power pallet feature made it a
negative thing and so maybe that's why
it's staying away from it if we don't
explore enough we see that actually this
is all the episodes it sound about ten
episodes so far maybe and it's already
playing pretty well compare this with
the really tiny worlds where we needed
hundreds if not thousands of episodes
before I learned anything am I using
tabular q-learning why can it learn so
quickly here it's approximate cue ending
with a small number of features it's not
much to be learned if your features are
just how close you to the next food
palate and how close are you to a ghost
then there's only two numbers to be
learned is how to trade those off once
you learn those numbers you're good to
go and that's why from a relatively
small amount of experience it's possible
to learn a cue function that's pretty
good so how do we justify this a little
more formally so we'll refer to
something called lisa queries here
hopefully many of you have seen that
before the notion of least squares is
that you have a bunch of points and
you'd like to fit a line through those
points at least in the simplest version
of least squares so how does that work
so we have a feature value F 1 just one
feature with a y the value we want to
predict and we have a bunch of red dots
which shows experiences samples of what
we should have predicted for those
specific feature values and the way
we're going to predict in the future is
by fitting a line to those points we're
going to say well I'm going to predict
it as some offset plus a slope
time's feature value and one line is
shown their question is what would be a
good line to choose you promised a a
line that's close to all the points but
what does it mean to be close to all the
points what does that mean like how do
we know which w0w one make this line
closest to all the points can we make
this mathematically formal just like
then ideally our Q values would be
mathematical in some formal way close to
the optimal Q values okay and alpha you
can do this in higher dimensions of
course when we estimate Q values it's
not going to be just one features gonna
be many many features now there's two
features here but in practice it might
be three four even hundreds or thousands
of features generalization for two
features then would be fitting a plane
through a set of points in a
three-dimensional space and then beyond
that we can't visualize it actually one
thing I want to note on the slides when
we have one of these it means that this
is something we think is really useful
for you to know but that we're now gonna
quiz you on on an exam that's what the
star means here so it's really good for
you to know this but we also know that
we don't require maybe you know our
prereqs the background that makes this
maximally easy to follow along and some
of you might not have that background
and so we're not gonna require you to
now go study that background to
understand these few slides but we think
most of you do have the background and
will benefit a lot from seeing where
this comes from
so least-squares what does it do it says
I'm gonna measure vertical distance of
my line to each of the points and I want
the sum of the squares of verticals
distances to be as small as possible
that's how I'm gonna measure how good my
line is so that would be this Y I hat is
my prediction there is why I which is
given and then I want to see the
difference squared Y square because if
we just average the differences that's
not a good measure because then
positives and negatives will cancel out
we need to make sure the positive and
negative errors don't cancel out because
both positive and negative errors are
bad so we square them sum it all
together and that's our objective our
predictions are in the form of a
weighted sum of feature values so that's
what it looks like so what we really
want to find then is a set of weights w1
two three and so forth such that this
thing is minimized in principle you
could try all possible settings of
weights see which one achieves the
lowest and that's the one you want but
these are continuous variables so trying
all possible settings of the weights is
not practical there's infinitely many
choices so we need a better way to find
the best setting of the weights so what
we're going to do is something a lot
like the local search you've seen in the
CSP lectures so let's say we had just
one point one term in that objective and
this will generalize to if we have many
points and we have this thing over here
can we do something close at the local
search what do we do in local search we
had a current choice of our variables in
this case our variables are W 0 1 2 and
so forth and can we maybe change that
choice to make it better and then repeat
repeat repeat and hopefully end up at
something good can we do the same thing
here well the question is can we do
something maybe even smarter instead of
just changing it and hope that it might
get better and otherwise reverted can we
know in which direction we should change
each weight should weight one go up or
down if we can decide that then we come
in a much more informed way get to a
good low error how do we know whether we
should move away to up or down well we
should say well if we change the weight
up or down does the air go up or down if
and we want the error to go down and
nudge the weight in the according
direction mathematically what that means
is we compute a derivative so you would
say what is my error which is my
function I'm trying to minimize as a
function of WM one of the weights and I
want to see the slope I want to say if I
change WM how much does my error go up
or down that's what this thing is saying
it's saying if I change WM and I make it
I do plus 1 for W M then this is how
much my error will change okay if we can
do that then we can do an update to the
weights we can say okay well I mean if
the slope is zero
no update needs to happen because that
way it does not affect the error but if
the slope is nonzero let's say the slope
is
let's say this is a positive slope if I
make W M go up the error will go up then
I did step in the opposite direction
step in a negative direction and that's
exactly what's happening here there's a
negative sign that negative sign has
disappeared
we step in the opposite direction of the
slope because you want to go downhill so
that's our update here for least squares
for that wait we can do that for all
weights and that's exactly what's
happening in the q-learning just as well
in q-learning we formulate an error
function a squared error function for
the current sample what is our sample
estimate what is our q function we can
look at the squared error take the
derivative with respect to a weight and
then based on that derivative that will
that will be this thing corresponding to
this thing over here this here
corresponds to this over here and that
tells us in which direction to step and
then we'll step scaled by alpha we
didn't fully arrived on the slides is
just meant to give you some intuition
behind why what we're doing in
approximate q-learning is actually well
justified
any questions about this yes okay
question was about the negative so let's
look at this again so what we're trying
to do we're trying to make the error as
a function of our weights as small as
possible what this derivative is saying
it's saying if I change WM by increasing
it by one unit
how much will my error go up but I want
to move in the direction where the error
goes down so this quantity here will be
positive if moving W up makes the error
go up but if that's the case you
actually want to move in the negative
direction and so that's why the negative
that ends up if we take derivative we
end up with a negative over here that
negative disappears when we look at the
update because we want to move in the
opposite direction of the up direction
on the error okay one thing to think
about and we'll look at this more in the
machine learning at the end of the
course is that you don't necessarily
want the more features the better you
can have too many features if you have a
finite amount of data for example
imagine you are fitting a function to
this set of points you might say well
let's fit a line and say okay that's my
line maybe it's even you find a least
squares error line and like okay but
it's still a bunch of error so you might
then say well not not so much a fan of a
line how about a parabola parabola
okay let's fit a parabola maybe now
you're a little happier what does it
mean to fit a line a line means that you
say Y is w 0 plus W 1 oops instead w1x
a parabola means that you say Y is w 0
plus w 1 x plus w 2 x squared if you
want a third order polynomial same thing
+ w 3x3 so as we want a higher order
polynomial what that means is we
introduce more features a new power of X
is a new feature and so as you introduce
more features you can start fitting this
more and more closely because you have
more flexibility the set of functions
Egret represents by a third order
polynomial is strictly more than you can
represent by a first order polynomial
because in fact they're all included in
the third order polynomial by just
setting some coefficient equal to zero
but you can set those coefficients to
non zero expanding the things you can
represent so you might wonder well what
if we fit let's say a 15th or their pawn
all melted this wouldn't that be nice
well maybe but this is what you get what
you see here is that if you just look at
the points that we're trying to fit it
does really well but then some other
places it does something that we likely
don't want it to do
that's called overfitting it's trying to
get all the points correct but as a
consequence it ends up doing some crazy
things in other places and so in
practice and we'll see a lot about this
in the late lectures you need to guard
against this kind of overfitting for now
the best way to think of is that you
don't always want just more and more
features because you'll have these weird
things come up and then crazy things
happen you might as well have anybody
draw some line through the points and
call it done okay so that's queue
learning now we're gonna see a different
approach to learning good policies to
act in worlds so I've seen value
learning we've seen queue learning now
we're gonna see policy search in policy
search you kind of just say hey there's
many policies to choose from
ultimately I want to end up with a
policy let's forget about learning Q
values V values let's just try different
policies and see which one is the best
and then we call it done because we
found the best policy okay so the reason
you might want this is because when you
have approximate Q values even though it
might work well if they're approximate
what they're approximating is
to get this least square error down on
this bellman equation and we know that's
related to good performance but it's not
directly tied to good performance its
approximating something that is related
to good performance can we do something
else well for example if you look our
two values it could be that some Q
values are much better than other ones
but the way they differentiate between
actions one of them picks the right
action that one picks the wrong action
the priority and Q learning is learning
Q values that are close not making sure
that the action that's the best is
favored of the action that's not the
best okay so what if we directly pay
attention to the actions policy learning
one way to do this we could say we start
with no K solution so we have Q values
and then we're gonna fine tune by
hill-climbing on the future weights what
does that mean we have some Q values and
then we can nudge the feature weights up
or down see what happens just like we
did in local search for CS peace if it's
better we keep the change if it's worse
we discard excuse me we discard it and
we repeat and over time we might find a
pause that's better and better and
better now what does it mean if a set of
weights is better or worse well you need
to execute the policy and see how well
it does now you might have to do this
many many times because the world is
stochastic and so sometimes maybe you're
lucky sometimes not so it can be
somewhat expensive and in general policy
search tends to be less sample efficient
means you need to collect more
experience to learn to do well with
policy search than you need with Q
learning but it's often a little easier
to understand what's going on you have
this policy you nudge it if it's better
you keep it if it's worse you discard it
and you go again okay so often people
will use a combination where maybe you
start curating fine-tuned policy
surgeons even other ways to combine them
which we're not going to get into here
let's look at some examples success
stories so here is a helicopter
helicopters are very difficult to
control you might wonder why you've
flown in a plane many times and you've
heard people say well if the pilot goes
to sleep the plane will still fly
because even if you make a paper plane
you just throw it in it flies it
naturally flies with a helicopter
actually it's not like that it's more
like a rock in the sky that wants to
drop I need to put effort into keeping
it in the sky at all times to think
about a little more carefully what's
really going on with a helicopter is
closer to let's say you have a very flat
surface maybe something like this by the
tray that you can hold but with no
boundaries to it just flat and it ends
at some point but there's not nothing
coming up on the side you have a marble
on it and now I need to walk somewhere I
need to make sure this marble doesn't
roll off your tray that's effectively
what pilots are doing when they're
controlling helicopters so it's really
hard if you don't adjust for it for
what's happening right now a wind gust
that comes in there are some other
perturbation that comes in then you
might be on your way down so you need to
pay a lot of attention as a pilot to
make sure to keep it in the air so it's
also hard to design controllers for this
but the three enforcement learning a
controller was designed for this
helicopter and let's take a look at this
helicopter in action
okay so this is extremely stable
helicopter flight now a couple is pretty
much not moving very hard to do even for
the best human pilots it's also upside
down so what's going on there you might
not have flown a helicopter upside down
or seen it fly upside down
how come this works to think about this
how do you control a helicopter you have
four control channels channel one is the
average angle of attack of the blades
and the steeper you make that the more
area push down the more thrust you have
Ganesh tools to make that negative you
make it negative you would go down very
quickly except if you are upside down in
which case the negative angle would keep
you up - it turns out it's more
efficient to fly this way any thoughts
why it's definite not more comfortable
but sorry I say it again so the answer
the answer there is the proposed answer
is all the thrust that you generate is
used to lift the weight of the
helicopter here whereas maybe if you fly
the normal way you're not using all the
thrust and that's exactly that's the
right direction but I'm gonna refine
that answer just a little bit if you
think about what happens when you keep a
helicopter up in the air you're pushing
air down force for the air down
helicopter gives the counter force to
stay up when you push that air down it's
much faster than it was before it's
going down quickly if he's gonna get
down quickly over the body of the
helicopter it's dragging that body down
and so your ham is kind of a double
effect of pushing air down you get a
counter force keeping you up but also
then you generate drag over the body of
the helicopter dragging you down or
trying to drag you down when you flip it
upside down that's not happening
you're still air coming over the body of
the helicopter but it's coming in from a
wider intake and only goes that have the
speed compared to the air that's coming
out and because drag is squared in the
velocity of the air you get four times
less drag flying this way than flying
the other way
you might wonder how do you control this
tray that you're kind of balancing your
marble on one thing is the angle of the
blades the other thing you control is
differential angle of the blades
throughout the cycle so for a helicopter
to move forward you can't just ask let's
move forward you actually have to tilt
the nose down and then the thrust will
be such that some of your thrust is
getting it to go forward once combined
with gravity how do you get your nose to
go down differential amount of air
pushed down front back left right allows
you to rotate the body of the helicopter
so that's the cyclic control and so
there's something in there called swash
plate that ensures that you go through
cycles of different angles of attack as
your blades rotate at something like
maybe 30 times per second you have a
fourth control which to make sure that
is you're facing the direction you need
to be facing if you don't have the tail
rotor what will happen is your
helicopter body would spin counter to
your blades but the tail rotor
compensates for that by also having a
differential angle of attack and you can
control that to then also decide which
way you want to look okay that's how it
copters you might also wonder why don't
people fly upside down I've wondered
that too um probably it's just not that
easy to build helicopters that humans
sit in in a way that is comfortable to
fly them yet then a also sustainable
flight upside down wouldn't principle be
more efficient here's another example
so here were gonna watch reinforce
fighting an action for a legged robots
what do you expect to happen here well
we know how reinforced learning works
initially it doesn't know what to do
it's exploring but then hopefully over
time it becomes better and better and
better and figures out what it should be
doing so it's just falling over it's
falling over again but it's falling over
a little later and it's better to fall
over later than earlier and it knows
that it's getting higher reward now and
now it's getting very high reward now
the beauty of reinforcement learning is
done you don't have to write
code for a new robot you just swapping a
new robot run the same code it can learn
to run here the robot starts on the
ground has some extra learning to do it
wasn't on the ground before it gets
rewarded for getting the head as close
as possible to standing head height the
closer the better and it figures it out
here this two of these robots are
learning together and they're practicing
soccer one of the beauties here aside
from how they run is that they can train
it each other so they can gradually both
improve and what they're able to do as
the goalie gets better the penalty
kicker needs to get better to get reward
and it can gradually get better and
better together you can do this with
real robots let me pause this for a
moment this is Brett the Berkeley robot
for the elimination of tedious tasks
Brett lives on the seventh floor of
citta Jedi Hall and in this video is
learning to play with a children's toy
this video is sped up a little bit this
takes about one hour in real time but it
is reinforcement learning to do
something that's never done before you
might say an hour is a long time because
you could do this first time at least I
hope y'all could do this first time but
it's not really true you could do this
first time because the first time you
did this was maybe when your
one-year-old and you might not have
succeeded first time around when you're
a one-year-old and so you need to think
of this reinforcement learning agent as
really a zero year-old hasn't done
anything yet is born in this world not
living on anything but getting rewarded
for putting that red block into the
matching opening and it just goes at it
until it optimizes how to get it in
there here's another example and it
pauses before we run this this is not a
Super Bowl it's a research collaboration
we've had with NASA on this robot you
might wonder why would they make a robot
this way and especially this one is for
planetary exploration so go
visit planets that maybe humans is hard
to send to but maybe a robot can go
explore for us
well what's beautiful about this robot
is that it's a sphere in some sense and
so what you really get is wheels in
every possible direction and Wheels is
what you need to get places the other
thing you get is view lengthen the
cables enough this thing can be
completely flat if it's completely flat
then it fits in a rocket very nicely
very small volume if you then expand it
again it can land with some damping so
you need smaller air box this way down
with a standard Rover that you might
land the only tricky part now is that
this is very non-intuitive to program
how it should do something but
reinforcement learning was able to solve
that problem and here we have a in this
case we had reinforcement learning run
in a simulated environment that
simulates this robot learn in simulation
after many many trials how to control
the simulated robot and that was then
deployed on the real robot and this is
tested here at NASA in Mountain View how
about a hand we use our hands a lot
clearly there's control involved can we
have reinforced winning learn to control
a hand let's see in robotics hands have
really proven challenging and the reason
it proves so challenging is because
Destin there's a lot of actions to be
taken at any given time there's a lot of
degrees of freedom and you need to
control them all the right way to get a
good outcome
most outcomes will be bad most outcomes
of controlling this thing will be the
cube drops on the ground and that's it
there's only a very small set of ways of
controlling this that I should lead to a
good result and how do you find that in
zoning on that here we're not gonna
watch the training we're just gonna
watch the final capability this is a
result done at Open AI and what we see
here on the bottom right is what it's
supposed to achieve and we see that
indeed it's capable of reorienting the
object that's holding to match up with
what's in the bottom right one of the
same thing here is that this one also
has trained only in simulation but it
turns out building sim
laterz for something like this that are
accurate is not practical but the agent
was trained in many many many simulators
and was trained in a way that it could
do well in all of these simulators and
it turned out that if it was good enough
to do well in all of these simulators
even though all of them were inaccurate
something that was good for all
inaccurate simulators was also good for
the real world so strategy to get
something to work in the real world is
get it working on many many different
simulators go robot there it is
so at this point we're not just
concluding this lecture we're actually
concluding the first stretch of the
course where we've seen in the first
stretch of the course is search csps
games MVPs and RL that's about search
and planning with a bit of learning
we're going to see in the second part
starting Tuesday is probabilistic
reasoning to deal with uncertainty and a
lot more learning to learn from data
rather than having a simulator ahead of
time available to you ok that's it for
today